Mss.Ms.Coll.200
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Commission to Henry Phillips, Dec. 18, 1869; 14x17-1/4; Missouri. Governor (1869-1871: McClurg)
    Jefferson City, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: J.W.McClurg Francis Rodman, sec.of state, by Eugene F. Freige. 1p. Seal. Attached is certification of document by Francis Rodman, sec.of state, of Missouri; Dec. 18, 1869.
  - Letter to ---, Dec. 19, 1869; Donders, [Franciscus Cornelis,] 1818-1889.
    A.L.S. 4p. Friendly letter. Engelmann lost chance for promotion in Holland.
  - Letter to [Charles] Mumford, Dec. 30, 1869; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
    New York, Thursday evening. A.L.S. 1p. and end. His Brooklyn lecture. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Letter to [Peter Martin] Duncan, Jan. 14, 1870; 8" x 5"; Cunningham, W. (William), 1849-1919
    King's College, A.L.S. 1p. Advises him of his election to the professorship of geology at the College.
  - Letter to [Richard] Owen, Feb. 2, 1870; Fowler, John, 1826-1884
    A.L.S. 2p. Asks for letter to introduction of Olliver in order to work out schedules, etc., for cross-channel trains.
  - Letter to W.M. Martin, Feb. 10, 1870; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
  - Letter to [Sir William Henry ?] Flower, March 1, 1870; 8" x 5"; Buckland, Francis T. (Francis Trevelyan), 1826-1880
    London, A.L.S. 4p. Reeparations for the Queen's visit to the museum.
  - Commission to Henry Phillips, Philadelphia, March 3, 1870; 10x8; Oregon. Office of the Secretary of State (Samuel E. Mays)
    Salem, Printed D.filled in in ms.S. 1p. On same sheet is attached clipping pertaining to Henry M. and Henry Phillips.
  - Commission to Henry Phillips, March 3, 1870; 14x17; Oregon. Governor (1866-1870: Woods)
    Salem, Printed D.filled in in ms.S. 1p. Seal.
  - Letter to [George Newbold] Lawrence, March 27, 1870; Cooper, James Graham, 1830-1902
    San Francisco, Cal., A.L.S. 4p.,end. Encloses his photograph [which is wanting]. Thanks for his photograph. Concerning work on California birds, and California geology.
  - Letter to [William Crawford] Williamson, April 7, 1870; Carpenter, William Benjamin, 1813-1885
    A.L.S. 4p. Deep sea life now known due to Capt. Spratt's dredging, and comments on the life.
  - Letter to J. M. Dorman, April 21, 1870; Bland, Thomas, 1809-1885
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning his box of shells.
  - Letter to [Sir William] Bowman, June 20, 1870; Snellen, H. (Herman), 1834-1908
    A.L.S. 2p. Discussion of Engelmann's children. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John Edward] Gray, Dec. 15, 1870; Thomson, Charles
    A.L.S. 4p. Botanical subjects. Sends items from the "Porcupine." Comments on Mr. Kent.
  - Letter to T. P. Barker, Jan. 23, 1871; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 3p. Concerning paleontological specimens and publications. Refers to his son and to Leo Lesquereux.
  - Letter to [Sir John Russell] Reynolds, London, Feb. 20, 1871; Sharpey, William, 1802-1880
    A.L.S. 3p. env., add. Asks for help in getting poor boy into Hospital for Epileptics, as favor for neighbor Mrs. Storrar. (See also A.L.S. of May 3, 1869.)
  - Letter to C. G. Brewster, Feb. 22, 1871; Orton, James, 1830-1877
    A.L.S. 3p. end. Discusses discovery of fossil shells in Valley of Amazon. Wishes to exchange specimens for copy of Gould and Billing's "Invertebrata of Massachusetts". Mentions Agassiz, Conrad, Silliman, Hall, Smithsonian, Phila. Acad., Yale College, Peabody Acad. (Salem).
  - Letter to [Edward] Palmer, March 6, 1871; 7x4-1/2; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 2p.and end.of 2p. Plants. Would like "a skeleton of a catcus giganticus." Refers to Parry, Engelman and Coues. Palmer's endorsement attacks Coues.
  - Letter to T. A. Cheney, March 8, 1871; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
    Ann Arbor, A.L.S. 2p. Proposed publication of his work. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s Mumford, March 28, 1871; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
    Ann Arbor, A.L.S. 4p. His lecture schedule. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Certificate issued to George B. Wood, April 20, 1871; 18" x 23"; New York Academy of Medicine
    D.S. by officers 1p. In Latin. Seal. (see G.B.Wood. Certificates...; no.12.)
    Not Found: 1/31/2011
  - Letter to Fraulein Gärtner, May 12, 1871; 11 1/4" x 9"; Levdig, Franz von, 1821-1908
    Tübingen, A.L.S. 2p. In German Acknowledges portraits of Joseph Gärtner and Friedrich Gärtner, her grandfather and father. Recalls Darwin's comments on Gärtner's work.
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s Mumford, May 15, 1871; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
    Ann Arbor, A.L.S. 1p. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Letter to [Charles Mumford], May 15, 1871; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
    Ann Arbor, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Authorization to International Lecture Bureau to make engagements for him during the 1871/72 season. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945
  - Letter to [Charles] Mumford, May 29, 1871; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
    Ann Arbor, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Letter to [James Graham] Cooper, June 7, 1871; Lawrence, George N.(George Newbold),1806-1895.
    Author presumed. Draft of A.L. 2p. Concerns birds of Alaska, Calif., Central America and Mexico. Mentions Grayson and Dall.
  - Letter to A[lpheus] Hyatt, June 19, 1871; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Suggests title format for Hyatt's paper on fossils.
  - Charter of incorporation, June 15, 1871; 19-3/4x24-1/2; Fairmount Microscopical Society of Philadelphia
    Philadelphia, D.S.by 11 members. 1p.and end. Parchment.
  - Letter to Henry [D. Chapman ?], July 15, 1871; Mivart, St. George Jackson, 1827-1900
    A.L.S. 2p.
  - Letter to Franklin Haven, July 15, 1871; 8x5; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, Mass., L.S. 3p. Asks for funds for the preservation of specimens during U.S.Coast and Geodedic Survey of the ocean floor. Refers to Capt. Cook and to Prof. Peirce.
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s Mumford, Sept. 15, 1871; 5" x 8"; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891
  - Letters to "Mother", 1871-1873; Lingne
    A.L.S. 6 letters. Concerns work with the U.S. Coast Survey, aboard the ships Bowditch and Hassler. Referes to H. Mitchell, Henck, Marindin and Pendleton.
  - Letter to [W.S. ?] Symonds, March 17, 1872; 7" x 4 1/2"; Pengelly, William, 1812-1894
    Lamorna, Torquay, A.L.S. 6p. Geological researches. Hippopotami.
  - Rossville Mission Indian vocabularies, April 15, 1872
    Xerox of D. 15p. Presented by Harcourt Brown; 2/27/70.
  - Letter to [Alphonse Milne-Edwards], April 19, 1872
    London, A.L.S. 3p. Thanks for his "magnificent work on the fossil birds of France" and his work on lemurs. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to William Hinckle, May 11, 1872; Allison, Joseph, 1819-1896
    A.L.S. 2p. Sends copy of "Home Letters" by Judge and Mrs. Joseph Allison.
  - Spencer F. Baird to E[dward] D. Cope, June 25, 1872; 8" x 8 1/2"; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    Eastport, Maine, 1 p. A.L.S. will be glad to prepare an article upon the fossil fauna of the Carlisle cave. FILM 403 FRAME 19
  - Letter to L.C. Miall, Aug. 20, 1872; 7" x 4 1/2"; Tylor, Edward B. (Edward Burnett), 1832-1917
    Linden, A.L.S. 4p. Proposed lectures on the "Early political and moral condition of mankind."
  - Letter to Mrs. Davey, October 4, 1872; Tylor, Edward B. (Edward Burnett), 1832-1917
    Linden, A.L.S. 3p., enc. wanting. Cannot provide a Darwin holograph but merely a signed letter. Also sends letters of Max Müller and Freeman.
  - Letter to ----, Dec. 3, 1872; 5" x 8"; Childs, George William, 1829-1894
    Phila., A.L.S. 1p. Is glad to hear that he is illustrating life to Lieut. Greble.
  - Letter to William Hinckle, Dec. 20, 1872; Allison, Joseph, 1819-1896
    A.L.S. 3p. Thanks for book by Thomas A. Rempis. Family news.
  - Letter to Joseph Harrison, Jr., 1872
    A.L. 3p. Locomotive experiments of 1831, done on New Castle and Frenchtown R.R. May be by William D. Lewis. Mentions Long, Stephenson.
  - Letter to [Rowland Gibson Hazard]:, Jan. - May, 1873; Hazard, Rowland
    Providence, R.I. A.L.S. 17 items. Relates primarily to business matters; investments in the Wisconsin Central R.R.
  - Letter to W. K. Brooks, March 20, 1873; 8x5; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 1p. Concerning his course in zoology for teachers.
  - Letter to ----, April 2, 1873; 8x5; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 3p. Says all applicants will be welcomed to the "Sea Museum School;" difficulty for summer school. Refers to Anderson.
  - Letter to S[amuel] A[dams] Drake, April 4, 1873; Lossing, Benson John, 1813-1891
    A.L.S. 2p. Concerning a Charles Willson Peale portrait of Washington.
  - Letter to "My dear Friend", April 10, 1873; 8-3/4x5-1/2; Haeckel, Ernst Heinrich Philipp August, 1834-1919
    Jena, A.L.S. 2p. In German Forwards publication. Forwards Léon Dumont's work on evolution, in Germany.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 4, 1873; Phillips, John, 1800-1874
    Oxford, A.L.S. 3p., enclosure wanting. Is forwarding the certificate "of one of the best of the many good men of England" for membership in the Royal Society.
  - Letter to Abrahams, April 1, 1874; 6x7-1/2; Schouw, William Frederick, 1807-1873
    London, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In German
  - Letter to Dr. Marten, April 1, 1874; Babington, Charles Cardale, 1808-1895
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning reeds in England.
  - Letter to Mr. [James] MacLehose, May 26, 1874; Kelvin, William Thomson, Baron, 1824-1907
    A.L.S. Requests copy of Chambers Encyclopedia; informs of upcoming marriage.
  - Letter to Mrs. Lionel Lucas, June 5, 1874; 7x4-1/2; Sylvester, James Joseph, 1814-1897
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning Venus fly-trap, electricity in plants, and refers to Burton Sanderson.
  - Letter to Mr. [James] MacLehose, June 15, [18]74; Kelvin, William Thomson, Baron, 1824-1907
    A.L. Tells of arrival of Encyclopedia, and review of proof copy "Verres".
  - Letter to C[harles] Appleton, Nov. 24, 1874; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Haeckel, Ernst Heinrich Philipp August, 1834-1919
    Jena, A.L.S. 4p. In German. Asks that Huxley review the Anthropologie. Research assistance through scholarship in German universities. Ontogeny.
  - Letter to Mr. Cooke, Nov. 25, 1874; Huggins, William, Sir, 1824-1910
    Upper Tulse Hill, Eng. A.L.S. 3p. Has been with Dr. Heaton and Miss Heaton at Leeds.
  - Letter to Monsieur Piedaguel, Passy, [Dec. 5, 1874 ?]; Flammarion, Camille, 1842-1925
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Astronomy. Working autobiography.
  - Copy of a joint resolution for the presentation of medals to Dr. Kane, etc., Feb. 15, 1875; 9-3/4x7-3/4 and 12-3/4x8; United States. Dept. of State
    Printed D.S.: Hamilton Fish. 1p.and enc.of 1p. Seal.
  - Letter to C. A. DeKay, April 9, 1875; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895
    New Haven, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning mastodon. Glaciers.
  - Letter to John Evans, June 4, 1875; Leidy, Joseph, 1823-1891
    A.L.S. 1p. Hopes that an invitation to visit W. Blackmore-which may prohibit his proposed visit with Evans-will not, therefore, be an inconvenience to him.
  - Letter to H. P. Child, Esqr., Kansas city, Missouri, July 15, 1875; Meek, F. B. (Fielding Bradford), 1817-1876
    White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia; A.L.S. 2 p. and envelope. Fossils of Missouri. Refers to his own work on Nebraska fossils.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", Aug. 13, 1875; Newton, Alfred, 1829-1907
    A.L.S. 7p. Comments on his former publication on birds, Which he understands is to be reprinted.
  - Letter to Miss Moseley, Jan. 12, 1876; Flower, William Henry, 1831-1899
    A.L.S. 3p. Due to inclement weather and illness, his wife will not accompany the group in their walk through the fields.
  - Letter to Jabez Hogg, June 10, 1876; Christie, William Henry Mahony, Sir, 1845-1922
    London, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning the measurement of angular apertures of immersion objectives.
  - Letter to Samuel S. Haldeman, June 30, 1876; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Biddle, Cadwalader
    Philadelphia, Photo.of A.L.S. 1p. Informs him that the University of Pennsylvania has conferred the degree of LL.D. upon him. Presented by Guy K. Haldeman, March 1967.
  - Letter to Professor Rogers, July 6, 1876; Kelvin, William Thomson, Baron, 1824-1907
    Niagara, Canada. A.L.S. 3p. Friendly letter. To visit Rogers in Newport.
  - Report on awards - Graham Bell's electric telephone and multiple telegraph, July 8, 1876; Centennial Exhibition (1876: Philadelphia, Pa.)
    Photograph of Ms.D. 3p. and end. Presented by Charles E. Hughes, Philadelphia City archivist, Dec. 1954.
  - Letter to Rev. H. Dyer, 1876; 8 3/4" x 8"; Otey, James Hervey, 1800-1863
    ca. A.L.S. 1p. and add. Mutilated Sympathy in bereavement. Presented by the Rev. James O.Patterson, Aug. 1955.
  - Letter to [Joseph] Henry, Smithsonian Institution, Jan. 13, 1877; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Bell, Alexander Graham, 1847-1922
    A.L.S. 1p. Wishes to bring guests to the medical museum. On same page is draft of letter from Henry to Bell;[Jan. 13, 1877].
  - Letter to [Alexander Graham] Bell, Jan. 13, [1877]; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878
    A.L.S. 1p. Draft. Advises no ladies to be guests at the medical museum. On same page as letter from A.G.Bell to Henry; Jan. 13, 1877.
  - Letter to [William] Archer, March 27, 1877; Balfour, John Hutton, 1808-1884
    A.L.S. 3p. Requests information about the "robust grass of which hand brooms are made for the purpose of sweeping carpeted rooms."
  - Letter to Monsieur Chasles, Paris, June 15, 1877; Institut de France. Académie des sciences morales et politiques.
    Paris, Printed L. filled in in ms. 1p.and add.,and end. In French. Notifies him of his election as foreign member.
  - Letter to William Simpson, July 16, [18]77; Martin, Isabella Mary
    A.L.S. 3p. Botanical information on "Venus looking glass" (incl. specimen). Also four misc. botanical notes, incl. speciment of Circassia from New Mount Athos, collected April 19, 1885. Found in Hooker, "British Flora," London, 1830.
  - Review of his "Der Darwinisms und seine Stellung in der Philosophie", ca. 1877; Dreher, Eugen, 1841-1900
    Autograph sketch of a review of his own recently published book, "Der Darwinismus und seine Stellung in der Philosophie" [i.e. Darwinisms and its place in philosophy], Berline Peters, 1877, which was to appear in the "Neue Stettiner Zeitung." No. p., no d., c.1877, no signature. 8 vo, 8 pages.
  - Miscellaneous papers, consisting of: Monday evening club proposals: Translation from "The Guide"-Louisa M. Alcott's "all of Us", 1877-1904; Lyman, Benjamin Smith, 1835-1920
    Translation from French geological society Compte-Rendu, March 7, 1904; and " Typewriting Speed Test Papers;" 1877-1904. D.and typed D. 56p.in 4 groups. Various sizes.
  - Letter to Dr. [P.L.] Sclater, Jan. 13, [1878 ?]; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lankester, E. Ray (Edwin Ray), Sir, 1847-1929
    Exeter Coll[ege], A.L.S. 3p. Recommends Moseley as a successor to Garrod. Comments on Sclater's article in the Nineteenth century review.
  - Letter to [William] Archer, [Jan.?], 30, 1878; Balfour, John Hutton, 1808-1884
    A.L.S. 3p. Refers to his representing the Royal Society of Edinburgh at a forthcoming function in London. Regrets he cannot attend the next meeting of the Microscopical Society.
  - Letter to General Richard Strachey, India, May 24, 1878; 7x4-1/2; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911
    London, A.L.S. 4p.and add. Meteorology. Refers to H.Smith. Boilers. Horace Darwin. Marriage of Sir Lewis Pelly. Friendly letter of London scientific life. Refers to Geological Society.
  - Letter to [Sir Richard] Strachey, May 24, 1878; 7x4-1/2; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911
    London, A.L.S. 4p. Forwards publications. Meteorology.Refers to Sir William Thomson, Horace Darwin, Sir Lewis Pelly, etc.
  - Letter to "My dear Friend", May 27, 1787; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893
    Folkstone, A.L.S. 6p. Discusses his state of health. Mentions Lady Lubbock and Spottiswoode.
  - Letter to Thos. A. Edison, July 11, 1878; Long, John Harper, 1856-1918
    Tübingen, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and end. (Contains also draft of Edison's reply) Experiments on the conductivity of heat in fluids; need for a finer thermometer. Presented by Charles Edison, April 1947.
  - Letter to John H. Long, Sept. 26, 1878; 5 1/2" x 8 1/2"; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931
    Menlo Park, N.J., 2p. and env. Relative to a tasimeter. Presented by Dr. Esmond R. Long, April 1947.
  - Letter to John H. Long, March 24, 1879; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918
    Ithaca, N.Y., L.S. 2p. Concerning Auerbach, but they have no opening at Cornell. Presented by Esmond R. Long; 1971.
  - Letter to Mr. Cooke, May 27, 1879; 7x4-1/2; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893
    A.L.S. 1p. Thinks he could do a book on the telephone, after his lecture before the Society of Arts.
  - Letter to Hugo von Meltzel, Hungary, Sept. 9, 1879; 3x5-1/4; Phillips, Henry, 1838-1895
    Xerox of A.L.S. on postal card. 1p.and add. In German. Corrects the spelling of his name and says he is not a "Doctor &c." From original in Magyar Tudományos Akadémia Kõnyvtára; 1968.
  - Letter to Hugo von Meltzel, Hungary, Nov. 15, 1879; 3x5-1/4; Phillips, Henry, 1838-1895
    Xerox of A.L.S. on postal card. 1p.and add. In English and German. Thanks for publication. Forwards photograph. From original in Magyar Tudományos Akadémia Kðnyvtára; 1968.
  - Papers relating to magic reciprocals and other mathematical principles, 1779, n.d.
    Typed D.: Gustavus Frankenstein and Mary F. Dick. ca. 60p. Presented by Mary F. Dick through the Library of Congress; 1949.
  - Letter to "My Dear Mrs. Austen;", Jan. 19, 187--; Buckland, Francis T., (Francis Trevelyan), 1826-1880
    A.L.S. 4p. His article fire "away shots every week at those 'miserables' who believe in Darwin and evolution," for he aims to be fishermen.
  - Writings on astronomy and physics, ca. 1870's; Huggins, William, Sir, 1824-1910
    A.D. 13p. Eng. Fr. Italian. Concerns work with the spectroscope. Discusses work work of A.C. Young and H.C. Vogel. Letter from W. Hazell, ed. of Huggins' 1872 work, "Spectrum Analysis." Mentions Father Leeche.
  - Letter to C. W. Ernst, Jan 10, 1880; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895
    A.L.S. 4p. His position supporting a limited geological survey of the "Public Domain" of the United States. Thanks for article on "Darwinism in our American Colleges."
  - Letter to ----, Feb. 10, 1880; Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, Isidore, 1805-1861
    A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning the Republic: wonders when his friend will assume the throne.
  - Letter to [H. P. Child], Esq., Kansas City, Mo., March 8, 1880; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    Wash., D.C.; A.L.S. 2p. Concerning snakes of North America with special emphasis on rattlesnakes. One is a lizard.
  - Letter to C. Meymott Tidy, Feb. 16, 1880; 10 1/4" x 8 1/4"; Royal Society (Great Britain)
    London, Printed L. filled in in ms. S.: T.H. Huxley, secretary. 1p. Acknowledges receipt of books.
  - Letter to [Sir Richard] Strachey, April 9, 1880; 7x4-1/2; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911
    A.L.S. 2p. Terminology for meteorology.
  - Letter to [Sir Richard] Strachey, April 9, 1880; 7x4-1/2; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911
  - Letter to J. E. Hilgard, June 14, 1880; 8" x 10"; Coues, Elliott, 1842-1899
  - Letter to ----, July 8, 1880; Langley, S. P. (Samuel Pierpont), 1834-1906
    Allegheny, Penna., A.L.S. 2p. Recommends John H. Long for the position. Presented by Esmond R. Long; 1971.
  - Letter to Lady Reay, Aug. 24, 1880; Rayleigh, John William Strutt, Baron, 1842-1919
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 4p. Travel plans change and their plans seem to always miss each other. Working on jets of water influence.
  - Letter to [Hugo von Meltzel], Dec. 28, 1880; 5-1/4x4; Phillips, Henry, 1838-1895
    Philadelphia, Xerox of A.L.S. 1p. In German. Concerning publications. From original in Magyar Tudományos Akadémia Könyvtára; 1968.
  - Letter to Mrs. Jeffreys, Jan.15, 1881; 7x4-1/2; Spencer, Herbert, 1820-1903
    A.L.S. 1p.,end. Cannot accept her invitation to dinner.
  - Letter to [Peter Martin] Duncan, April 6, 1881; 7 1/4" x 4 1/2"; Cunningham, W. (William), 1849-1919
    King's College, A.L.S. 3p. The Council of the College invites him to accept the Chair of Mineralogy along with that of Geology.
  - Letter to Mr. Hilgard, May 5, 1881; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895
    A.L.S. 1p. Asks for paper of his brother, which was read at the National Academy.
  - Letter to W[illiam] H[enry] Huntington, Paris, June 4, 1881; 8x5; Stevens, Henry, 1819-1886
    London, A.L.S. 2p. Forwards publication. Concerning H.O. Houghton and praises him and his printing. Originally in Huntington collection: H O16.97:St45. Henry Stevens. Stevens historical collection...
  - Letter to W[illiam] H[enry] Huntington, Paris, June 4, 1881; 8x5; Stevens, Henry, 1819-1886
    London, A.L.S. 1p. Introduces H. O. Houghton. Originally in Huntington collection: H O16.97:St45. Henry Stevens. Stevens Historical Collection...
  - Letter to Charles R. Hildeburn, June 14, 1881; Thompkins, Hamilton
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. Is researching the Association of Loyalists.
  - Letter to Hugo von Meltzel, Hungary, Sept. 3, 1881; 9-1/2x6; Phillips, Henry, 1838-1895
    Philadelphia, Xerox of A.L.S. 3p.and end. In German. Thanks for publications. From original in Magyar Tudonányos Akadémia Könyvtára; 1968.
  - Letter to Samuel F. B. Morse, Sept. 13, 1881; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895
    A.L.S. 1p. Thanks for his abstracts, and will publish them.
  - Letter to W. F. Denning, Oct. 14, 1881; Christie, William Henry Mahony, Sir, 1845-1922
    London, A.L.S. 2p. Wishes his communication on comet observation for publication in Observatory.
  - Letter to Hugo von Maeltzel, Hungary, Dec. 30, 1881; 9-1/2x6; Phillips, Henry, 1838-1895
    Philadelphia, Photo.of A.L.S. 2p. In German. Has not received publications. Has worked on Egyptian hieroglyphs. Will visit Europe. From original in Magyar Tudományos Akadémia Konyvtára; 1968.
  - Letter to C[harles] R. Hildeburn, Feb. 7, 1882; Smith, Lloyd P. (Lloyd Pearsall), 1822-1886
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning Library Company of Philadelphia business.
  - Letter to Mr. Martin, Feb. 23, 1882; 7x4-1/2; Brown, A.
    Edinburgh, A.L.S. 3p. Wishes to borrow a copy of Peter Williamson's Edinburgh directory for reprinting.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", March 28, 1882; Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Has decided not to revise his talk on the Yucatan in order to publish it in the North American Review.
  - Letter to A. Brown, April 22, 1882; 8x5; Guild, James Wyllie
    Glasgow, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning Peter Williamson's Edinburgh Directory.
  - Letter to [R.E. Thompson], May 4, 1882; 5 1/2" x 8 1/2"; Coues, Elliott, 1842-1899
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Letter to Honored Lady [Miss Hassler], May 6, 1882; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Zschokke, Emil, 1808-1889
    Aarau, L. 2p. Translation. Concerning his translation of the memoirs of Ferdinand Rudolph Hassler. On same sheet are: same to same; May 30,1882: and, Switzerland, Library...to Zschokke; May 20, 1882.
  - Letter to "Gentlemen", May 11, 1882; Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. Requests support for W. E. Lafford, a student of natural history.
  - Letter to [Sir Richard] Strachey, May 18, 1882; 6-1/4x4; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911
    A.L.S. 2p. Meoteorological matters.
    Not Found 1/31/2011
  - Letter to [Emil] Zschokke, May 20, 1882; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Aargauische Kantonsbibliothek
    Aarau, L. 1p. Translation. Thanks for memoirs of F.R.Hassler. On same sheet as: Zschokke to Miss Hassler; May 26, 1882 and May 30, 1882.